Off we start a new פרק perek today, במה אשה, Bameh Isha,
the sixth פרק. perek. These are in the chapters that are about
all the things that you have to do in preparation for שבת,
Shabbat, just to remind us of the context. So we started with
the whole issue about
הוצאה Hotza'ah and getting involved in things before מנחה. Mincha. But anyway,
they really kicked in in the second פרק, perek, which was about
lighting candles, and then we got onto the third פרק, perek, which
was about putting the food on the fire. Fourth
פרק, perek, sort of insulating it. Fifth פרק perek is about what
your animal can have on it on שבת, Shabbat, which means what
you have to take off of your animal before שבת. Shabbat. And
I think I pointed out at that time that it's sort of,
we sort of went through the first פרק perek feeling it was
very not relevant to us, but it is not so relevant to
us because we don't have these farm animals. But if you think
about it, what it really did is it changed what שבת Shabbat
meant or what ערב שבת Erev Shabbat meant, that it wasn't just
what you were doing in the home, but going down to the
barn, going down to the stable, making sure that the animals are
free from these burdens. That having your animal not work doesn't just
mean not taking it to the field and plowing it, but
really unburdening it and making sure that it had its שבת, Shabbat,
and that was an important part of the preparations. And now we
go to what you can be wearing on שבת, Shabbat, and therefore,
in a way, it's not so much about ערב שבת Erev Shabbat
because it's what are you dressing yourself with on שבת Shabbat as
well, but also what are you putting on on Friday afternoon, and
therefore in this lead up to these preparations of getting ready for
שבת, Shabbat, which is when we actually enter. So we have six
days of חול Chol and a seventh day of שבת. Shabbat. We
have six פרקים prakim of preparations, and the seventh פרק perek will
get us to a direct discussion of the מלאכות melachot of שבת.
Shabbat. So we begin now our sixth פרק, perek, which is what
you can be wearing on שבת Shabbat itself, what is considered clothing,
what is not and so on. So let's take a look as
we begin. במה אשה יוצאה. Bameh isha yotza. So interestingly it begins
with a woman, not a man, because a lot of these concerns
have to do with that a woman might, or anybody but particularly
concerns around a woman's clothing and jewelry, that she might take it
off and show her friend and come to carry it. And it's
worth reading the first רש"י Rashi inside because he basically says, like
in our previous פרק, perek, there are two major concerns here. One
is biblical, one is rabbinic. If you look at רש"י, Rashi, במה
אשה יוצאה, Bameh isha yotza, what can a woman go out with?
דהוי תכשיט ולא משא. Dehavi tachshit velo massa. The first concern is
let's make sure that what she's wearing is considered either jewelry or
clothing, but not a burden. So there are some things you could
wear on your body that are essentially a burden. I'll give you
an obvious example, a backpack. Okay? So not just because you're wearing
it makes it not a burden. So the first question is what
types of things are clothing or jewelry which are okay, as opposed
to a burden which is not okay. And here, by the way,
I should also mention that as opposed to animals where we didn't
always exactly get what was in the okay category, like the exact
conceptual line wasn't always clear, here it's easier to understand. Fundamentally for
people, in order for it to be okay, it has to be
defined as clothing or jewelry. And anything that is not clothing or
jewelry is considered to be a burden. So the first issue is
determining that. What are things that are not in the clothing and
jewelry category and are a burden and are a problem.
And now רש"י Rashi says that's a biblical issue. Now there's a
second issue which is a rabbinic issue. ואיכא דהוי תכשיט, Ve-ika de-havi
tachshit, there are some that actually are jewelry and are therefore biblically
okay. וגזרו בהו רבנן, Vegazaru beih rabbanan, but the rabbis said not
to wear it. Why? דילמא שלפה, Dilma shalfa, maybe she'll take it
off, ומחויא לחברתה, U-machavya le-chaverta, and show her friend. Oh look at
this nice ring I have, look at this nice tiara. לחשיבותא, Le-chashivuta,
to show its importance, to show how nice it is. ודילמא אתי
לאתויי ארבע אמות, Vedilma ati le-asuyei arba amot, and then she'll walk
four אמות amot before putting it back on her ring or on
her head. Therefore there's a biblical concern of something that's not considered
clothing or jewelry and a rabbinic concern that it will be taken
off and be carried without being put back. And we had that
by the animals as well, things that were loose and the saddle
blanket and all that that might fall off and come to be
carried. Two types of concerns. Our משנה mishnah doesn't tell us which
category, which problem it's dealing with, but as we'll see in the
גמרא, Gemara, fundamentally this first משנה mishnah is addressing itself to the
second issue, the rabbinic issue, things that really are jewelry but nevertheless
it's a rabbinic problem that they might come to be taken off
and carried. So let's take a look now and read the cases
in the משנה. mishnah. במה אשה יוצאה ובמה אינה יוצאה. Bameh isha
yotza u-ve-mah eina yotza. What can a woman go out with and
what can she not go out with? לא תצא אשה לא בחוטי
צמר ולא בחוטי פשתן. Lo teitzei isha lo be-chutei tzemer velo be-chutei
pishtan. A woman cannot go out with wool strings that would be
like woven into her hair or flax strings. ולא ברצועה שבראשה, Velo
be-retzuah she-be-roshah, or some type of a strap that she would be
on her head, maybe on her forehead, maybe wrapped around her hair.
ולא תטבול בהם עד שתתירם. Velo titbol bahem ad she-tirpaim. And number
two, also if she's going to the מקוה, mikvah, she can't go
to the מקוה mikvah with these strings woven into her hair until
she actually loosens them. Okay, because the water, yeah, you could still
be wearing... Yeah, you could wear it, technically you could wear it
as long as it's loose enough that the water can get between
it and your hair. Okay, so that seems to be just a
parenthetical remark, but we will see in the גמרא, Gemara, the גמרא
Gemara will treat it not so parenthetically. Okay, ולא טוטפת ולא סרביטין,
ve-lo totfet ve-lo sarbitin, she cannot wear a טוטפת, totfet, like that
word's not familiar, טוטפות, totafot, so it seems to be right, no,
but that wouldn't be, but right. But it's some type of an
amulet or some type of a thing presumably that's worn on her
head. And not בסרביטין, be-sarbitin, which also is some type of a
thing worn on her head. We'll see what this is in the
גמרא. Gemara. בזמן שאינם תפורים, bi-zman she-einam tefurim, if they are not
knitted into like a hairnet. The גמרא Gemara is going to work
with an assumption, first of all that we're talking about married women.
Well, it's going to work with an assumption that women are always
wearing some covering. So presumably it's also working with an assumption that
we're talking about married women. Although, you might be aware and this
is not our topic at all, that there are some that believe
that even unmarried women have to cover their hair. Anyway, the גמרא
Gemara is going to work with the assumption that a woman is
always covering her hair, presumably a married woman. So she's got these
various things that are hanging down from her hair, you know, something
on her forehead or we'll see something hanging down on the sides
of her head. So if they are woven into her hairnet or
into her cap, then there's no concern that she'll remove them because
a woman would never remove her cap in the public domain. She
would never have her hair uncovered in the public domain. So therefore,
it's not a problem. That's, but if they are separate from her
hairnet, then we are afraid that she will come and take them
off and show them to her friend. So these types of things,
these amulets or whatever, or these things hanging down on her, on
her temples, these are a problem if they are not woven into
her hair covering.
So they're not wearing these expensive ones, even if they're like the
cheap, you know, crazy kind of thing?
Well we'll see. Well we'll see. The גמרא Gemara is not explaining,
we will see. Right, but that's a good point, right, if the
concern is that she'll take them off, maybe only certain types. So
we'll see in the גמרא. Gemara. The משנה Mishna is not distinguishing.
Exactly.
ולא בכבול לרשות הרבים, ve-lo be-khvul li-reshut ha-rabim, and she also cannot
go out with a כבול khvul into the public domain. A כבול
khvul is also some type of a hair covering but it was
an additional hair covering or we'll see in the גמרא Gemara exactly
what this was. She cannot go out into the public domain. Now
I want to just stop a minute on the word public domain
because it seems like this is only going on the last case,
ולא בכבול לרשות הרבים. ve-lo be-khvul li-reshut ha-rabim. But really it would
seem that like everything should be, you know, the point is don't
go out into the public domain. So actually what we are going
to find in the גמרא Gemara is a, is a much stricter
read of this משנה. Mishna. That really all the first things that
said a woman cannot go out with, we don't only mean can't
go out into the public domain, and we don't only mean cannot
go out into a כרמלית karmelit which is rabbinically like a public
domain, but we even mean she can't go out into the חצר,
khatzer, even to the courtyard, right? So they would have houses around
a courtyard, they'd have a courtyard which would effectively have walls, the
houses would have walls. So maybe it wouldn't be her total private
domain but it would be close to that, you know, it's not
exactly, the analogue is not exactly our backyard but it's close to
that. A few houses would open into it. And even though it
was a רשות היחיד, reshut ha-yakhid, they didn't want her to go
out. Why? Because if we let you go out into the courtyard,
you'll come to take it out into the street, into the רשות
הרבים. reshut ha-rabim. And all of this is because not because it
per se is carrying, but it might lead to taking it off
and might lead to carrying. So it seems quite extreme how much,
you know, we are normally we say you don't make a גזירה
לגזירה gezera li-gezera except, you know, we say that except for all
the times when we do. Okay, so you know the phrase is
it's all one גזירה. gezera. But okay, it was all part of
the same point. We don't want it be worn at all anywhere
outdoors, even in a courtyard which is a private domain. But the
one exception in your house you can wear it. The one exception
is this כבול khvul which that we only limit in a רשות
הרבים reshut ha-rabim in the courtyard is okay. And the גמרא Gemara
is going to say because, you know, it would not we could
not have have made it so impossible for women to wear any
type of, you know, of jewelry or any type of, what are
these like accoutrements that would have been overly burdensome. So many things
we outlawed even in the courtyard, but some things we, you know,
even if we there no we didn't allow רשות הרבים, reshut ha-rabim,
we still allowed in the courtyard and that was this כבול khvul
is one of them. We will see what the כבול khvul is
in the גמרא, Gemara, but it was basically some type of a
hair covering. ולא בעיר של זהב, ve-lo be-ir shel zahav, not with
a golden city, presumably this was some type of like a tiara
or something, you know, that would look like that look like ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, you know, they always do those like those like skylines, what
are those called, not skylines, you know what are those called? Skylines.
Skylines, you know, whatever, so imagine you have like a tiara I
guess that looked like that, something of that
nature. So ולא בקטלא, ve-lo be-katla, not with a קטלא katla which
is also some type of a jewelry. We'll see what more what
this is in the גמרא. Gemara. Maybe a type of, well we'll
see in the גמרא. Gemara. ולא בנזמים, ve-lo bi-nezamim, not with earrings.
Earrings? People pull earrings to show to her
friend?
So okay we'll see what it is in the גמרא. Gemara. ולא
בטבעת שאין עליה חותם, ve-lo be-taba'at she-ein aleha khotam, and not with
a ring. So she can't wear earrings or finger rings, a lot
of things she can't be wearing if there's no עירוב. eruv. If
there is no seal on it. Now that makes it only because
if there's no seal it's not a carrying problem. problem, it's purely
an ornament, but it is a concern she'll take it off. If
there is a seal, it's worse. Then it could be a carrying
problem because then it's not fundamentally about jewelry. Okay, ולא במחט שאינה
נקובה, v'lo b'machat she'eina nekuva, not with a needle that does not
have a hole, because then like sort of like a pin, let's
say like you know type of a hat pin or something like
that. So these things technically are jewelry and therefore are not a
biblical problem. They're only a rabbinic one. And therefore it ends ואם
יצאה אינה חייבת חטאת. v'im yatza eina chayavat chatat. If she does
go out with any of these or really any of the things
in the משנה, Mishnah, it's only a rabbinic issue, not a biblical
one. None of these are technically carrying and therefore she's not חייבת
חטאת, chayavat chatat, but if she was wearing let's say a ring
with a seal or a needle with a hole in it, then
it would not be considered jewelry and then actually it would be
חייבת חטאת. chayavat chatat. Okay, so it would be even worse. So
the first whole משנה Mishnah is only rabbinic issues, and the real
question is going to be like too bad Rifka isn't here because
Rifka would tell us when she was living in Brooklyn and there
wasn't an עירוב, eruv, but you know, how does this translate nowadays?
If there's no עירוב, eruv, do women not wear, you know, take
off all of their rings and all of their jewelry and don't
wear any of that outside? I mean that would seem to be
the application of this משנה. Mishnah. So we will see. Do you
have a question Ari? No?
Does the עירוב eruv make it like a חצר? chatzer?
So that's a good point also. Maybe even an עירוב eruv shouldn't
work. If I've just been telling you excellent question. If I've just
been telling you that this is אסור assur even in a חצר,
chatzer, so how is an עירוב eruv better than a חצר? chatzer?
And therefore it should be אסור assur even in an עירוב. eruv.
Okay, so let's get up on the בימה bimah tomorrow on שבת
Shabbos and announce that no women can have, can wear any of
their jewelry outdoors, you know, the only thing you can wear is
your hair covering. So we will have to, what?
Yeah, you don't think that will work. Okay, so we will have
to see how this all translates. And Ari makes an excellent point.
If it's a problem in a חצר, chatzer, it should be a
problem even with an עירוב. eruv. Let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so the גמרא's Gemara first question is טבילה מאן
דכר שמיה? tvila man d'char shemeih? Interesting, jumps over the whole the
first points, goes straight to the idea: don't go into the מקוה
mikvah with these hair strings unless you loosen them. Who mentioned טבילה?
tvila? What does that have to do with anything? You know, רש"י
Rashi says מאי עניין טבילה אצל הלכות שבת? mai inyan tvila eitzel
hilchot shabbat? Like מאי עניין שמיטה אצל הר סיני? mai inyan shmita
eitzel har sinai? So what did you mention? Of course it's a
very funny question because if you remember in the last פרק, perek,
it said you know these types of of collars can be worn
on a בהמה, behema, and you know you can טובל tovel them
on the neck of the בהמה behema and פרה אדומה, par aduma,
once we're talking about them let's say some other הלכות halachot about
them. But the גמרא, Gemara, you know, asks this question because it's
got an answer. So let's see what the גמרא's Gemara answer is.
So אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר רבה בר אבוה. amar rav
nachman bar yitzchak amar rabba bar avuha. A softball.
Right,
מה
טעם קאמר, ma
taam kaamar, or you know or what what the academics would say
is that נחמן בר יצחק Nachman bar Yitzchak was said his opinion
about how reading טבילה tvila as related to the איסור issur of
carrying and then the גמרא Gemara raised the question to set up
introducing רב נחמן בר יצחק. Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak. So you know
that's always an issue. רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak
was not necessarily responding to the question of the גמרא. Gemara. He
might have just been interpreting the משנה, Mishnah, but the גמרא Gemara
phrased it as a question to set up רב נחמן בר יצחק's
Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak statement. Anyway, so that would be one way
of reading of understanding how this was put together. Anyway, רב נחמן
בר יצחק אמר רבה בר אבוה, Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar Rabba
bar Avuha, מה טעם קאמר. ma taam kaamar. You have to read
the משנה Mishnah as the טבילה tvila is giving you the reason
for why a woman cannot wear these hair strings. Why? מה טעם
לא תצא אשה לא בחוט של צמר ולא בחוט של פשתן? ma
taam lo teitzei isha lo bechut shel tzemmer velo bechut shel pishtan?
And why should she not go out with these wool strings woven
into her hair or the flax strings? Now you understand what's bothering
him because other types of things, jewelry, you might want to take
off and show and say oh look at my nice tiara, look
at my nice ring, whatever it is. But this is a string,
it's like a wool string woven into the hair. Why would you
take it off? What's the concern? So he says ah, that's why
we mentioned טבילה. tvila. The טבילה tvila is telling you the reason
why these strings are a problem on שבת. Shabbos. Why? מה טעם
לא תצא אשה לא בחוט של צמר ולא בחוט של פשתן? ma
taam lo teitzei isha lo bechut shel tzemmer velo bechut shel pishtan?
Why can't she go out with these strings? She's not going to
take them off to show her friend. מפני שאמרו חכמים mipnei she'amru
chachamim because the rabbis said בחול bachol in the weekday לא תטבול
בהם עד שתרפם. lo titbol bahem ad sheterafem.
She cannot go into the מקוה mikvah until she loosens them. וכיון
דבחול לא תטבול בהם עד שתרפם vekeivan debachol lo titbol bahem ad
sheterafem
and since in the weekday that's the הלכה, halacha, בשבת לא תצא,
beshabbat lo teitzei, don't wear them on שבת. Shabbos. Why? דילמא משתרמי
לה טבילה של מצוה? dilma mishtarmi lah tvila shel mitzvah?
Maybe she'll have to go to the מקוה, mikvah, there'll be a
טבילה של מצוה, tvila shel mitzvah, which is an interesting idea. What
does that mean like she'll have to go to the מקוה mikvah
for because you know she's a נדה nidda for her husband? So
that would be the most obvious. What else could it be? She
touch well yeah or זבה zava right, but a נדה nidda is
the more obvious one, or she of she what, she touched a
שרץ sheretz and then she has to eat תרומה truma or something,
but of course she can't eat תרומה truma till the night and
she goes to the מקוה. mikvah. So presumably it's talking about going
for the מקוה, mikvah, so the phrase
then is from נדה, nidda, משתרמי mishtarmi means like it chanced upon
her. Like she she knew before שבת Shabbos when she'd be going
to the מקוה mikvah but anyway, let but if she's we allow
them to wear, when they have a need to go to the
מקוה mikvah on שבת, Shabbos, and you're allowed to go to the
מקוה, mikvah, people are allowed to go to the מקוה mikvah on
שבת, Shabbos, so what will she do? She'll have to go to
the מקוה mikvah and she's wearing this, this is what she normally
wears on שבת, Shabbos, these strings in her hair, ושריא להו, v'sharya
lehu, and she'll undo them. I just want to say by the
way a linguistic point. You know שרי, shari, שריא, sharya, people who
are, you know, used to reading the בבלי Bavli means permitted, like
allowed. But the same, but the words we normally use אסור assur
and מותר mutar are really words about knotting.
אסור assur means bound, bound with ropes. And להתיר l'hatir means to
undo the ropes. מותר. mutar. So if it's אסור, assur, it's like,
you know, it's it's bound up, it's prohibited. If it's מותר, mutar,
it's freed, it's permissible. So what?
Like a prison, בית אסורים. beit asurim.
בית אסורים, beit asurim, exactly,
exactly, exactly. So it means to bind, to knot, and so on.
So therefore it is she is מתיר אותם, matir otam, she doesn't
allow them, but she undoes them. Okay, she therefore she would come
to ושריא להו, v'sharya lehu, she'll come to undo her the strings
from her hair so she has to go to the
מקוה. mikvah. ואתי לאתויינהו ארבע אמות ברשות הרבים. v'asi l'asvunehu arba amos
birshus harabbim. And then she comes out of the מקוה, mikvah, she
gets dressed, but, you know, but she's not going to maybe not
bother put the strings back in her hair, her hair is wet
anyway. So anyway, she'll carry those in רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. So
the problem with the strings is not that she'll take them off
to show her friend, the problem is she might take them off
when she's going to the מקוה mikvah on שבת Shabbos and not
put them back on. Now תוספות Tosafos of course asks the question.
תוספות Tosafos says, so does that mean, I mean, say that about
anything you're wearing. You know, you might go to the מקוה mikvah
and take it off and not put it back on. So תוספות
Tosafos basically says no, you know, things that are obviously major items
of clothing you'll put back on. But things like this which are
minor items are things that we're afraid that you're not going to
bother, you're just going to go straight home and ugh, who has
the time to put it weave it back in the hair and
you'll just carry it. So, you know, and that specifically is because
it's a very trivial part of the clothing we're afraid it would
not be put back on.
And how's the husband might take exception if she took that extra
time before going home.
Yeah, that could be too if it's in the נדה niddah context.
Yeah.
What if she's wearing a pocket?
Oh, wearing a pocket, what do you mean wearing a pocket?
A string in a pocket in her clothing so she's physically not
holding.
Oh no, that doesn't matter. You can carry things on your body
and not only carrying in your hand.
And then it'll be okay?
No, it would not be okay. That is considered carrying, right. It
does not matter even if it's in like a pocket.
So essentially it means some women need those strings.
Exactly. Because we don't want women to be wearing this in their
hair because it'll lead to cases where they'll carry. Okay.
So let's take a look.
בעי מיניה רב כהנא מרב. baei minei Rav Kahana mei Rav. So
רב כהנא Rav Kahana asked from רב. Rav.
שכי חלוליתא מאי? shikhi chalalita mai? What about types
of like braids or strands that are like that are like what
do you call it, like chain-like.
You know, have a lot of holes, you know what I mean
chain-like right, they're like links. So that type of a thing, water
can get
through. אמר ליה *amar lei* ארי קאמרת *ari kamarta* woven that you're
talking? כל שהוא אריג לא גזרו *kohl shehu arig lo gazru* you're
right that was out of the category. They're talking about like single
strand some type of thing like this which is again I don't
know the exact thing that it's described but something that has more
like these holes and is porous and things loose and that you
would not come to take off in the מקווה *mikvah*. That wasn't
in the category. That's okay. You can wear it too. Yes because
we have no concerns. No concerns you'll show it to your friend,
no concerns you'll take off to go to the מקווה *mikvah*, that's
fine. איתמר itmar, נמי *itmar nami* it was also taught אמר רב
הונא בריה דרב יהושע *amar Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua* כל שהוא
אריג לא גזרו *kohl shehu arig lo gazru* anything that is like
this type of a you know sort of like woven thing which
presumably means that it's loose and has holes, that's not a problem.
ואיכא דאמרי *v'ika d'amri* others say אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע
*amar Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua* חזינא לאחוותי *chazina l'achvasi* I saw
my sisters דלא קפדן עלייהו *d'lo kapdan alaihu* they weren't מקפיד makpid
*makpid* about them which means that they didn't you know did not
care to take them off when they went to the מקווה *mikvah*.
It's interesting how he sees what sisters are wearing when they go
to the מקווה *mikvah*. I don't know. Maybe they came maybe he
saw them afterwards and their hair was wet and this was wet
also so he figured somehow he sees that his sister didn't care
about you know were not concerned to remove these. רש״י *Rashi* actually
says it's not just the מקווה *mikvah* it means they weren't concerned
to remove these when they went to bathe or when they went
to shower and you know whenever they went and רש״י *Rashi* assumes
that you'll be more concerned if you're trying to clean yourself and
clean your hair so you'll be more concerned to remove things that
get in the way than you would be because of the הלכות
*halachos* of מקווה *mikvah*. I mean now for the הלכות *halachos* of
מקווה *mikvah* we go crazy to make sure that everything is off
regardless but technically as we saw before if there's it's loose or
there's holes in it and water can get through you could wear
it to the מקווה *mikvah*. But now if you're trying to take
a shower and you're trying to wash your hair you're going to
take them off, right? So רש״י *Rashi* says that the way he
reads this statement is that who was it who said this? רב
הונא בריה דרב *Rav Huna brei d'Rav* right רב הונא בריה דרב
*Rav Huna brei d'Rav* said my sisters wouldn't take them off even
when they went bathing, even when they went you know to wash
themselves and wash their hair so they was so much that water
could get through them you know even in that case they weren't
they didn't care. So presumably that's just okay a nice you know
a nice story that supports the idea that water gets through them
and you don't have to wear them in the מקווה *mikvah* and
you don't have to take them off before going to the מקווה
*mikvah*. But let's see what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* does with this.
It says מאי איכא בין האי לישנא ובין האי לישנא *mai ika
bein hai lishna u'vein hai lishna*? What difference does it make whether
you say that anything that's אריג *arig* they didn't they didn't prohibit
because the water could get through or this statement that he focused
on the fact that his sisters didn't mind them when they were
on them when they went to bathe? So מאי איכא בין האי
לישנא ובין האי לישנא *mai ika bein hai lishna u'vein hai lishna*?
איכא בינייהו דתניפם *ika beinihu d'tanifam*. Let's say they are dirty, they're
soiled, these are braids, the strings. להאי לישנא דאמר כל שהוא אריג
לא גזרו *l'hai lishna d'amar kohl shehu arig lo gazru* if you
say that anything that is woven they were not גוזר *gozer* was
not in the category of forbidden האי נמי אריג *hai nami arig*
so this is also woven and it wasn't in the category. להאי
לישנא דאמרת משום קפידא *l'hai lishna d'amarta mishum kfeida* but the one
that emphasized whether people are מקפיד makpid *makpid* are concerned to remove
them or not כיון דתניפא מיקפד קפיד עלייהו *keivan d'tanifa mikpad kapid
alaihu* since they're dirty they would be מקפיד makpid *makpid* to take
them off. Now what does this mean? So רש״י *Rashi* says רש״י
*Rashi* has two explanations. The first explanation is like this. Look even
if they're dirty they won't be a חציצה chatzitzah *chatzitzah* problem because
water can still get through them. So therefore one approach says that
what we said yes or no was not that case by case
we're going to assess are you going to care to take them
off or not. We have to make הלכה halacha *halacha*. We have
to make categories. So the categories we're going to make is something
that is you know generally not a מקווה *mikvah* issue is not
a problem. Something that generally is a מקווה *mikvah* issue is a
problem because you'll come to take it off and you'll come to
carry. So these types of braids even when they're dirty if we
put them in the not a problem category they remain in the
not a problem category even though right now if I'm going to
the מקווה *mikvah* because they're dirty I'm going to take them off.
Not taking them off because of הלכות חציצה hilchos chatzitzah, *hilchos chatzitzah*.
I'm taking them off because I don't want my hair to get
dirty with them on right? If they're dirty they're going to get
into water it's going to make my hair dirty. So yes it's
true in this case I'll come to take it out but you
know what? Tough luck. חז״ל *Chazal* did not say said that these
were in the no problem category even though granted in this circumstance
I have reason to take it off. So that's answer number one.
Answer number one is it's all based on מקווה *mikvah* criteria and
therefore even in if in a particular case you'll take them off
because they're dirty still if they're not a מקווה *mikvah* problem חז״ל
*Chazal* let you wear them. The other הלכה halacha. *halacha* seems to
be more case by case. He says my sisters wouldn't be you
know would let them on or would you know and therefore weren't
מקפיד makpid *makpid*. That seems like it's not לא גזרו *lo gazru*
a category, it's let's look at the individual circumstance. So if in
this individual circumstance they're dirty and you'll take them off, we're not
going to let you wear them on שבת Shabbat. *Shabbos*. Why? Because
same reason. You'll go to the מקווה *mikvah*, you'll take them off
not because of the laws of מקווה *mikvah* but because you don't
want to get your hair dirty and therefore you'll come to carry
it. So the basic difference is one is a more classic הלכה
halacha *halacha* approach which is a categorical approach. We figure out what's
the... category things are in, we don't judge each case by its
particular circumstances. And the other says he was focusing on whether his
sisters were מקפיד makpid or not, so he says in any case
where somebody is going to be מקפיד makpid not to go into
the water with them, that's going to be forbidden and we will
look at each case individually and even if it's just מקפיד makpid
because it's dirty, still that's going to be forbidden. So that's the
two approaches. Now I should say something about רשי Rashi has an
interesting approach that his רבותיו Rabosav say which רשי Rashi does not
like and this is interesting in terms of laws of מקוה. mikvah.
רשי Rashi says that קפידא להו kopida laihu means that even not
just that they would take them off because they don't want to
get their hair dirty, it means that since they would not want
them in their hair because it'll get their hair dirty, you also
becomes a הלכה halacha. of מקפיד makpid and it also becomes a
מקוה mikvah problem. You might be aware that the criteria for מקוה
mikvah is that it's a problem if it's either if it's the
majority of the body which is almost never or even if it's
a minority of the body a חציצה chatzitzah an obstruction if you're
מקפיד makpid. if you don't want it there. So רשי Rashi quotes
his רביי Rabbaim who said that the problem here is if it's
dirty and she doesn't want it there when she's going into the
מקוה mikvah then it even is a it even becomes a מקוה
mikvah problem because then it becomes a מקפיד makpid something you don't
want on your body. But רשי Rashi says that doesn't make any
sense because if water gets through it which is what we're assuming
then why should מקפיד makpid? matter? Even if it's something you don't
want on your body that's only an issue if it prevents water
from getting through it. And this actually becomes an interesting question in
הלכה. Halachah? You have something on your body that you don't want
on there but water can get through it is it a חציצה
chatzitzah problem? And basically we rule like רשי Rashi against his רביי
Rabbaim and we say it's not a חציצה chatzitzah problem. That the
issue of being מקפיד makpid is only a problem if it already
does the physical job of obstructing water. If it's not obstructing the
water I don't care how much you want it or don't want
it you can't call it a חציצה chatzitzah. okay but I did
want to mention that about the word.
So if it's on you and and if it's on
you and prevents if it's on you and prevent yes if it's
on you and prevents water from getting through but you are nevertheless
not מקפיד it is not considered a חציצה. chatzitzah For something to
be חציצה chatzitzah it has to have two criteria it has to
physically prevent the water from getting on your body and you have
to be מקפיד. And that is well we're not learning הלכות מקואות
hilchos mikvaos so I'm not going to have to answer that but
that I just wanted to point out that this is an interesting
opinion here that does is discussed in הלכה halakhah that maybe מקפיד
alone defines it as חציצה chatzitzah even if the water gets through
but רשי Rashi clearly rejects that. Yes.
A shirt water can get through right?
Yes so technically technically if you had a shirt a porous shirt
you could you know like a total covering or whatever you know
I mean obviously with the pants and everything that won't necessarily get
through but yeah then you could go to the מקוה mikvah in
that. I mean לכתחילה l'chatchila we have nothing on even when it
doesn't fall into the laws of חציצה chatzitzah. but technically speaking comes
up to issues also when women convert and you know you need
a בית דין beis din there how do you know covering the
body and so on yes so.
Question when when a woman goes for מקוה mikvah she is she
is clean before make sure she is clean before she goes into
a מקוה. mikvah. So how do you justify something dirty on her
touching those water?
Well that's why they would take them off.
No no but I'm saying if it's loose and and water can
still flow through.
Right so the opinion was was that okay it's look again what
we do right now in terms of how clean we get and
you know we're a little excessive in terms of what like might
be strictly required or strictly done in the time of the גמרא
Gemara but that's number one. But number two is is that although
it depends how you read various סוגיות. sugyos. But number two is
is that this again isn't on her the reason we get totally
clean is so that there shouldn't be an obstruction a חציצה. chatzitzah
The thinking here is is that it'll they're like muddy strings and
it'll but it'll wash off in the water or you know it
won't prevent water from getting through so that's the concern you wouldn't
want it you wouldn't want to be getting muddy in the process
but it's not a חציצה chatzitzah, problem because water will get through.
So but you're right the real when we take when we scrub
everything even things that are presumably porous and we get everything off
that's because we go we're more מחמיר machmir than is strictly demanded
okay and we are לכתחילה l'chatchila we don't want anything on even
if it's porous. Yes.
Could you say that if it's water cannot get through you could
still be alright if you're not מקפיד?
Yes and that's very important if you have things like you know
certain types of casts or other types of things sometimes you have
things on the body or bandages other types of things braces things
like this you know where water can't get through but if you're
not מקפיד it's okay it's a very important category of הלכה. Anyway
we're going to continue. Okay תנן התם tnan hatam now that so
that's the issue anyway that the מקוה mikvah issue ties in to
the carrying issue. תנן התם tnan hatam over there in מקואות mikvaos
so now we're going to discuss מקוה mikvah a little bit. ואלו
חוצצים באדם v'eilu chotzitzim b'adam the following things are חוצצים chotzitzim for
people meaning because before it was talking about things that are חוצצים
chotzitzim for vessels obstructions that make it a not good טבילה tevelah
and the following are חוצצים chotzitzim for people
חוטי צמר וחוטי פשתן chutei tzemer v'chutei pishtan you'll notice it directly
parallels the first two of our משנה mishnah right the wool and
the and the and the and the linen strings in the hair
so again and that's our משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah* assumes that you don't
go to the מקוה mikvah *Mikvah* with them and the understanding is
that's why also you don't wear them on שבת Shabbat, *Shabbat*, but
then it goes on, ורצועות שבראש הבנות *Veretsuot sheberosh habanot*. So the
רצועות *Retzuot* the straps, right, also mentioned in our משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah*,
the first three in our משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* exactly those three, the
wool and the linen strings and the straps, okay, רבי יהודה Rebbi
Yehuda אומר *Rabbi Yehuda omer* so exactly the three that are the
first three listed there of a חציצה chatzitzah *Chatzitzah* are the first
three listed in our משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah* about what you don't wear
on שבת Shabbat, *Shabbat*. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda אומר *Rabbi Yehuda omer*,
רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda, *Rabbi Yehuda* says: של צמר ושל שיער אין
חוצצין *Shel tzemer veshel sear ein chotzetzin*. Wool and hair, like if
you had hair knotted on itself or you have some type of
or you know some type of, yeah, but no because it's woven
into your hair. So some type of foreign hair that's woven in,
that's not a חציצה chatzitzah. *Chatzitzah*. מפני שהמים באין בהם *Mipnei shehamayim
ba'in bahem*. He feels that water can get between these types of
strings on hair or hair on hair, so he agrees to the
linen that that will hold very tight and water won't get through,
but water will get through here and he does not have a
problem. The תנא קמא Tanna Kamma *Tanna Kamma* did not mention hair,
we don't know the תנא קמא's Tanna Kamma *Tanna Kamma's* opinion on
hair, we will discuss that in a minute. Okay, אמר רב הונא
*Amar Rav Huna*, וכולם בראשי הבנות שנינו *Vechulam beroshei habanot shaninu*. All
of this is talking just in the hair. Okay, so that was
pretty, that was said already, what's point are you trying to make?
So מתקיף לה רב יוסף *Matkif lah Rav Yosef*, למיעוטי מאי *Lemiutei
mai*? What are you coming to exclude by that statement? אילימא למיעוטי
דצואר *Ilima lemiutei detzavar*, if you're saying that these strings around the
neck are not a problem, ודמאי *Vedemai*? So what isn't the problem
if it's around the neck? אילימא למיעוטי דצמר *Ilima lemiutei detzemer*, wool
around the neck? השתא רך על גבי קשה חוצץ *Hashta rach al
gabei kasheh chotzetz*, if something soft like wool on something hard like
hair is a חציצה chatzitzah. *Chatzitzah*, if it's a חציצה chatzitzah, *Chatzitzah*
in the hair, רך על גבי רך מיבעיא *Rach al gabei rach
mibaia*? Of course if it's soft on soft, if it's wool on
the neck, it'll be a חציצה chatzitzah. *Chatzitzah*. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
assumes and I really don't understand this, but somehow like if you're
doing something soft around something stiff, that won't conform maybe as much
to the object it's surrounding so it'll leave some gaps and maybe
wouldn't be a חציצה chatzitzah. *Chatzitzah*, but if it's around something soft,
you know, it's more easy to conform. But you know, I don't
get it at all, it would seem to me very obvious that
you could put something in your hair that really blocks it from
getting to individual hairs and something on your neck because it's more
pliable actually, you know, you would think that there would be more
gaps. So I don't exactly get the גמרא's Gemara *Gemara's* assumption but
anyway let's still read it. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says but it
certainly should be a problem on the neck. אלא למיעוטי דחוטי פשתן
*Ela lemiutei dechutei pishtan*. Okay, so we're talking about linen strings, that's
a problem in the hair but not the neck? No, השתא קשה
על גבי קשה חוצץ *Hashta kasheh al gabei kasheh chotzetz*, if hard
on hard, linen is considered hard and hair is hard, is a
חציצה chatzitzah. *Chatzitzah*, קשה על גבי רך מיבעיא *Kasheh al gabei rach
mibaia*? How much more so hard on soft? So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* basically assumes that if the object that you are obstructing is
soft, then it more likely will be a חציצה chatzitzah. *Chatzitzah*. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says if it's a problem in the hair,
it's certainly a problem around the neck. אלא אמר רב יוסף Amar
Rav Yosef, *Ela amar Rav Yosef*, היינו טעמא דרב הונא *Hainu taama
deRav Huna*. Here's the reasoning of רב הונא *Rav Huna* why it's
not a problem around the neck: לפי שאין אשה חונקת את עצמה
*Lefi she'ein ishah choneket et atzmah*. Because actually you don't make it
as tight around the neck. If you tried to make it tight,
you're right, maybe it would get tighter than it would be around
the hair, but you're not going to choke yourself. So if you
have something around the neck, by definition you're going to keep it
looser, so it's not a problem if it's something around the neck
because people will weave things tighter in their hair than they do
put necklaces around their neck. So איתיביה אביי Abaye *Eitiveih Abaye*, אביי
*Abaye* asked him this: הבנות יוצאות בחוטין שבאזניהן *Habanot yotzot bechutin shebe'ozneihen*
אבל לא בחבקים שבצואריהן *Aval lo bechabakim shebetzavareihen*. The young girls can
go out with strings in their ears, they would wear this as
a way of preventing their ear piercing from closing up. Now that's
an interesting point, it's very nice you're not afraid they'll take it
out because they want to keep it there to prevent the hole
from closing, but why is it considered
clothing or jewelry? It's not there to protect the body, it's not
there to look nice, it's just there to protect the hole from
closing up. So I just raise that now, we'll bracket that for
now, but we're focusing on the next part, they cannot wear the
chokers around their necks. So why can't they wear those chokers? Presumably
it's similar to this מקוה mikvah *Mikvah* discussion, because they would have
to take it off to go to the מקוה mikvah *Mikvah*. ואי
אמרת דאין אשה חונקת את עצמה *Ve'ei amrat de'ein ishah choneket et
atzmah*, but if you say that women don't like choke themselves when
they make things around their neck, חבקים שבצואריהן אמאי לא *Chabakim shebetzavareihen
amai lo*? Why not? Now you could have said maybe it's something
beautiful and you'll take it off because it looks nice, but the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes you're still dealing in the category of things
that are only a problem because you'll take them off to go
to the מקוה mikvah *Mikvah*. So it says why would you take
off these chokers? You just said you don't have to take off
necklaces around the neck. אמר רבינא *Amar Ravina*, so says רבינא *Ravina*,
הכא בקטלא עסקינן *Hacha bekatla askinan*.
We're talking about a קטלא *Katla*. Okay, now רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says
a קטלא *Katla* is a, let me just see one thing here,
yeah, קטלא *Katla* was mentioned already in the משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah*, ולא
בעיר של זהב ולא בקטלא *Velo be'ir shel zahav velo bekatla*. Okay,
so a קטלא *Katla* was רש"י Rashi *Rashi* understands some type of
a like of a bib or an apron that was worn, but
it had a tight choker-like at the top of it. Others understand
that קטלא *Katla* just refers to something around the neck, but anyway
we're talking about a choker or something that at least has a
choker as a component of it. דאשה חונקת את עצמה *De'ishah choneket
et atzmah*. There's some types of things that women wear, not necklaces,
but chokers where the idea is to make it
very
tight. Why? The neck is, you know, should make it look more
fleshy. Why? There are very tight chokers, right? But is—but they're not
to make the neck look fleshy, are they? No.
They're to make it look more sexy, says Bobby. Okay.
Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says, that's the גמרא's Gemara explanation, but
it says, yeah, there are chokers that are a problem. So yes,
if there's a choker, it's an issue because you'll have to take
it off to go to the מקוה mikvah. and therefore you can't
wear it. Okay. But if it's a looser necklace, that's not a
problem. And again, what I just remind us that there issue about
the string in the ears raises interesting questions about why is that...
why is that considered clothing. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara continues
to the next... to the next line in the משנה. Mishnah רבי
יהודה אומר של צמר ושל שער אין חוצצין מפני שהמים באין בהם.
Rebbi Yehuda Omer shel tzemer veshel se'ar ein chotzim mipnei sheha-mayim ba'in
bahem. Or not the next line of the משנה, Mishnah well yes,
but the line of the משנה Mishnah in מקוואות, Mikvaot, not our
משנה. Mishnah So talking still about חציצה, chatzitzah רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda
says that actually wool and the hair strings in the hair is...
is not a problem and neither is hair... hair strings in the
hair or hair tied on itself because water gets through them. So
אמר רב יוסף, this is within הלכות חציצה, chatzitzah not directly about
שבת. Shabbat אמר רב יוסף אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל Amar Rav
Yosef Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel הלכה כרבי יהודה בחוטי שער. Halachah
ke-Rebbi Yehuda bechutei se'ar. We rule like רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda by
strings of hair. Doesn't say... maybe not by the wool but by
the hair. Hair is not a חציצה chatzitzah on itself. That raises
interesting questions because one of the things as Bobby was mentioning about
the preparations for the מקוה mikvah is getting out all the knots
in your hair and pulling out hair that has knots. But actually
להלכה, le-halachah, very... not in all cases but in... there are many
cases in which hair knotted on itself is not considered a problem
because we say that the water can actually get through the knots,
which is funny, you would think that it's very tight hair on
hair. So anyway, he says we rule like רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda
we rule like רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda. by hair. So אמר ליה
אביי, Amar lei Abaye, אביי said, הלכה? You mean we rule like
him? מכלל דפליגי. miklal de-pligi. It's... you're inferring that he argues. But
the Rabbis only talked about wool, they never talked about hair. וכי
תימא אי לאו דשמיענא מתנא קמא דאיירי בחוטי שער איהו נמי לא
הוה מיירי. vechi teima i lav deshame'ina mi-tana kama de-ayri bechutei se'ar
ihu nami lo havei mairy. No, if רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda had
not known that the Rabbis said that hair was a problem, he
wouldn't have bothered to mention hair. So the fact that רבי יהודה
Rebbi Yehuda said hair is okay suggests that the Rabbis said hair
is no good. That's not true. ודילמא כשם קאמר להו. vedilma keshem
qamar lehu. Maybe he's drawing an
analogy. כי היכי דמודיתו לי בחוטי שער, ki heichi de-modisu li bechutei
se'ar, says, look, we all agree hair isn't a problem, hair woven
into hair is not a problem, you agree to me on that
point, says רבי יהודה. Rebbi Yehuda, אודו לי נמי בחוטי צמר. odu
li nami bechutei tzemer. So why don't you also admit to me
that wool woven into hair is not a problem? So just because
he mentions hair doesn't mean that that's also debated. He might be
mentioning hair just to say we can all agree on the hair,
let's also say... agree that the wool is not a problem. Okay,
so anyway, there's a question about whether there is a debate or
not, but there does not seem to be a question that we
rule that hair woven into hair is not an issue, is not
a חציצה. chatzitzah איתמר, it was said, אמר רב נחמן אמר שמואל
Amar Rav Nachman Amar Shmuel מודין חכמים לרבי יהודה בחוטי שער. modin
chachamim le-Rebbi Yehuda bechutei se'ar. That actually you're right, everybody agrees that
hair woven into hair is not a
חציצה. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, חוטי צמר חוצצים חוטי שער
אין חוצצים. chutei tzemer chotzetzim chutei se'ar ein chotzetzim. Wool is a
חציצה, hair is not a חציצה. רבי יהודה אומר של צמר ושל
שער אין חוצצין. Rebbi Yehuda Omer shel tzemer veshel se'ar ein chotzim.
Neither of them are a חציצה. So here you see that the
תנא... tana... the real debate is about the wool, but that everybody
agrees about the hair. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק Amar Rav Nachman
bar Yitzchak מתניתין נמי דייקא. matnitin nami diyka. You can actually read
this out from a close read of the משנה. Mishnah דתניא, de-tanya,
because our משנה Mishnah says by שבת, Shabbat remember שבת, Shabbos. יוצא
אשה בחוטי שער בין שלה בין של חברתה. yotzeh ishah bechutei se'ar
bein she-lah bein shel chavertah.
So our first משנה Mishnah says that a woman cannot wear wool
strings in the hair, right? Which we say... and that it was
a חציצה. So we've established that wool is no good, that can't
be the רבי יהודה position, רבי יהודה says wool is okay. Our
משנה Mishnah said wool is no good. Then another משנה Mishnah coming
up says that a woman can wear hair woven into her hair,
whether it's her own hair or her friend's hair. So basically a
later משנה Mishnah. says hair is not a problem and the first
משנה Mishnah said wool is a problem. So מאני? mani? Who is
this going like? אילימא רבי יהודה? ilei-ma Rebbi Yehuda? If it's רבי
יהודה, אפילו חוטי צמר נמי? afilu chutei tzemer nami? Then he should
be arguing even by the wool. אלא לאו רבנן? ella lav Rabbanan?
You see that we're going like the רבנן Rabbanan because in our
משנה Mishnah they say wool is a problem, ושמע מינה, u-shema minah,
and then in the later משנה Mishna they say hair is not
a problem. ושמע מינה בחוטי שער לא פליגי. u-shema minah bechutei se'ar
lo pligi. They don't disagree by hair. שמע מינה. shema minah. So
we will discuss this because I agree, again, intuitively we would say
if anything hair on hair is can be very tight and it
should be a חציצה. Here the גמרא Gemara is saying while wool
and linen as strings are an issue and is a חציצה and
therefore it's a שבת Shabbat issue, hair on hair is not a
חציצה and not a שבת Shabbat. issue. So we will discuss that
more when we get to that next משנה Mishna where the גמרא
Gemara will get more into that question about hair, when is hair
a חציצה and when is not a חציצה on hair.
Yes. This almost implies she could go in the מקוה mikvah, wearing
a wig.
Well, not a wig because a wig is not a hair knotted
into other hair, it's a tight scalp cap
around.
even shaved the
way some people do.
Right. Okay.
ולא בטוטפת velo vetotefes and not with a טוטפת. totefes. So now
we go beyond the מקוה issues, right? So the first things are
things you normally wouldn't take off and therefore the only reason that
there were problems was because you would take them off for the
מקוה. Now we move into the category of things that you might
take off to show somebody and we're not dealing with מקוה issues
right now. Okay, so and the first of that list is the
טוטפת. totefes. ולא בטוטפת. velo vetotefes. מאי טוטפת? mai totefes? What is
this
טוטפת? totefes? אמר רב יוסף חומסא דקטיפתא. Amar Rav Yosef chumsa de-katifta.
A bundle of like spices. רש"י Rashi says that was there to
ward off the עין הרע. ayin hara. Okay, so some type of
a of a little packet of spices a person would wear, I
don't know, on their head, around their neck somewhere for עין הרע
ayin hara purposes.
Now, אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, so now you know my
initial response to that would be that then it shouldn't only be
a rabbinic problem, then it should be a biblical problem because it's
not clothing, it's not a תכשיט, tachshit, it's being worn as a
form of a רפואה refuah that you're carrying around on your person.
But the גמרא Gemara says the opposite, it should be totally okay
then. אמר ליה אביי תהא כקמיע מומחה ותשתרי. Amar lei Abaye tehei
k-kameia mumcheh v-tishtarei. We will see later that amulets are, certain amulets
that are proven to work, proven effective, nine out of ten patients,
anyway, that those amulets actually can be worn on שבת. They're not
a biblical problem, they're not considered carrying, and they're not even a
rabbinic problem. We're not afraid you'll come to take them off. I
mean, if they're doing a good job, why would you, you know,
and they're protecting you, why would you take them off? So we'll
discuss again that later also. Why is an amulet not considered why
is it considered clothing even if you think it's effective? But anyway,
the גמרא Gemara says if that's what this is doing then it
shouldn't be a problem at all, it should fall into the law
of of these amulets.
Why isn't it considered superstition?
We will get discuss that as well. I know, we will discuss
that as well, don't worry. When we get to the amulets we
will have a very fun discussion and I will and I will
I will bring in the רמב"ם Rambam who was a super rationalist
who had what to say about amulets and so on. Okay, so
don't worry about that, we will get to it. So אלא אמר
רב יהודה, Ella amar Rav Yehuda, said רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, it's
not this is not what it is, it's not a little spice
pack. So אמר רב יהודה משמיה דאביי אפוזינו. amar Rav Yehuda mishmeih
d-Abaye apuzaino. Oh, it's an אפוזינו, apuzaino, where that really explains it
all. So the גמרא says, so what is this אפוזינו? apuzaino? So
it seems to be some type of a, like you know, some
type of a head ornament. I really don't,
I think שטיינזלץ Steinsaltz gave some speculation about what the what the
root word was. Anyway, it's some type of a head ornament which
you probably could have figured out from the word טוטפת, totefes, okay
from טוטפות. totafot. Anyway, תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we taught
similarly: יוצאה אשה בשבכה מוזהבת. Yotzei isha b-shvacha muzhevet. She can go
out with a golden, you know, hairnet or hair covering. You're going
to show me a picture of a woman what? Yeah, no, but
that's a cap, that's not, no, that's טוטפת. totefes.
Yeah, I don't know how he knows that. Alright, anyway, it's some
type of a head ornament. So anyway, we taught a woman can
go out with a golden hairnet. Now why can she go out
with a golden hairnet? Why aren't we afraid that if it's nice
and golden and attractive she'll take it off? So this is the
point that I said which is we don't, a woman would not
uncover her hair in the public. So if this is her basic
hair covering, even if it's beautiful, she's not going to take it
off to show her friend. She would not uncover her hair. So
therefore she can go out with this golden
hairnet המזוהבת ha-muzhevet ובטוטפת u-ve-totefes and with a טוטפת totefes ובסרביטין u-ve-sarvitin
and סרביטין. sarvitin. Those were the two things mentioned in our משנה.
Mishna. הקבועים בה. ha-kvuim bah. So remember our משנה said תפורים, tforim,
this says קבועים, kvuim, but it's the same point. If they are
attached to the hairnet, it's not a problem because you won't take
off the hair, the only way you would take them off is
by taking the hairnet off. And we were not afraid you'll take
off the
hairnet. איזו טוטפת ואיזו סרביטין? Eizu totefes v-eizu sarvitin? So what is
this טוטפת totefes and what is this
סרביטין? sarvitin? So אמר רבי אבהו טוטפת המוקפת מאוזן לאוזן. Amar Rabbi
Abbahu totefes ha-muketfes me-ozen l-ozen. It's something that goes from ear to
ear. Okay, so ben assuming that it's some type of a, you
know, maybe a headband. וסרביטין המגיעין לה עד לחייה. v-sarvitin ha-magiin lah
ad l-chayeha. And סרביטין sarvitin is something that goes down to her
like jaw. So you know, I think you see this sometimes in
like those headdresses, you know, from Egypt. I remember in the Met
or whatever, you know, you have these things that are going down
the side of the head. Okay, so basically if you have something
going on the forehead, the side of the head, these types of
things, they could be woven into and attached to the headdress. If
they're attached to the headdress, no problem, because you're not going to
take off the headdress, you would never reveal expose your hair in
public. But if they're separate from the headdress, then it's a problem,
then you might come to take it off and therefore and therefore
you cannot wear them. So that's what these are, various types of
things worn, ornaments worn on the hair, sometimes woven into the headdress,
presumably some type of a forehead band and some type of a
thing that goes down by the temples. אמר רב הונא
עניות עושות אותן של מיני צבועין.
Amar Rav
Huna aniyot osot otan shel minei tzvuin. So too bad Michael isn't
here
anymore. and the point of making this is presumably not just an
interesting anthropological point but to say that it doesn't have to be
of a precious metal to be something that's attractive and you want
to show somebody. Look at this beautiful ceramic thing, you know, look
at how nicely painted it is. So even if it's not of
a precious metal it could still be something that is very nice
and attractive and especially within a person's socioeconomic group and is this
problem that you will come to take it off and show. So
that is the issue about again we're now onto nice jewelry that
you'll show, not things we're afraid you'll take off for the מקוה,
and the first were these various things that are worn on the
forehead or by the temples which if they're woven into the hat
are not a problem, if they're separate they are a problem. Yes.
The fact that it even gets mentioned implies that there must have
been some level of wealth in בבל Bavel
that they could have gold and silver. Yeah. I think that is
true. Okay ולא בכבול velo vikhvul now. She cannot wear this כבול.
kvul. What is this כבול? kvul? So אמר רבי ינאי amar Rabbi
Yannai בכבול זה איני יודע מהו. bekhvul zeh eini yodeia mahu. So
thank you we can now feel good. He says I don't know
what this כבול kvul is. But now but he actually did not
was not clueless, he had two possibilities. אי כבלא דעבדא תנן, ee
kavla de-avda tenan, it might be something that slaves wear that's called
a כבול kvul that they would wear something that would basically identify
you know whose slave they were, like so you know it would
be like a tag or something around their neck, או דילמא כיפה
של צמר, o dilma kippah shel tzemmer, or maybe it is a
type of a wool hat. Okay and a wool hat כיפה. kippah.
Right. Now it's a wool hat which we could be afraid she'll
take off because she has this other thing which we were talking
about, the שבכה. sevakha. So the שבכה sevakha is a thing she'll
never remove but she might remove another type of a covering, an
additional covering, this wool hat. So I don't know which one we're
talking about. And it's not necessarily that they're both true. Why? Because
אי כיפה של... ee kippah shel... אי כבלא דעבדא תנן... ee kavla
de-avda tenan...
I'm sorry I'm sorry I skipped a line. Let me read it
again. אמר רבי ינאי Amar Rabbi Yannai כבול זה איני יודע מהו.
kvul zeh eini yodeia mahu. אי כבלא דעבדא תנן, ee kavla de-avda
tenan, are we talking about the one worn by slaves, או כיפה
של צמר שפיר דמי o kippah shel tzemmer shapir dami she can
wear the one on her head, the hat, because again even though
it might be an additional hair covering it's still a hair covering
and she won't come to take it off. או דילמא, O dilma,
or do I say כיפה של צמר תנן, kippah shel tzemmer tenan,
no we're talking about the hat the covering on her head and
אי... וכל שכן כבלא דעבדא, ee... vekholsheken kavla de-avda,
and that where even we're afraid that the covering on the head
she'll take off and how much more so will we be afraid
that a slave will take off you know his sort of the
thing around his neck that identifies him. So basically what we say
is we it's clear to us that this identification worn by the
slave is concerned he'll come to take it off and the question
is does כבול kvul also refer to a hat worn by a
woman. She has something else to cover her head, will are we
afraid that an additional covering the hat will she that she might
come to take that off or we'll say no if it's there
to cover head even though it's additional she won't come to take
it off. So there's two ways of reading it whether that's a
concern about the hat of the woman. Now before we get to
the hat of the woman I should say it's interesting though by
the identifying sort of like I don't know necklace around the around
the slave it's only a concern he'll come to take it off.
If you remember by the animals the dogs if a collar was
there for identification purposes by the string around the chicken for identification
purposes it was considered a burden right if you remember that was
considered not something that's there but here if it's an identification around
the slave it's not considered it's considered a form of clothing maybe
that's the way slave clothing but it's quite interesting that it is
not a parallel הלכה here the only concern is you'll come to
take it off. So let's see what the גמרא says about this
issue of the hat. Is the hat a concern?
So אמר רבי אבהו amar Rabbi Abbahu מסתברא mistabra it makes sense
כמאן דאמר כיפה של צמר תנן keman de-amar kippah shel tzemmer tenan
that the hat is a concern. ותניא נמי הכי ve-tanya nami hakhi
the wool hat. יוצאה אשה בכבול, yotzei ishah bikvul, a woman can
go out with a כבול, kvul, this is you know exactly what
we're talking about the
כבול, kvul, ובאיסטמא u-ve-istama ואיסטמא ve-istama לחצר. le-hatzer. Okay we don't know
what an איסטמא istama is either but now we're going to go
on but she can go out where into the חצר hatzer not
into the רשות הרבים. reshut harabbim. ורבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר אף
בכבול לרשות הרבים. ve-Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer af bikvul le-reshut harabbim.
Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar says
she can even wear this כבול kvul into רשות הרבים. reshut harabbim.
So still how do you see what the כבול kvul is? So
let's keep on going. כלל אמר רבי שמעון בן אלעזר, klal amar
Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar said a general rule:
כל שהוא למטה מן השבכה, kol she-hu lemattah min hasevakha, now you
would have assumed and I would have assumed that a כיפה kippah
would have been above the hairnet okay but he says no actually
it
is a hair covering like we've been assuming but it goes underneath
the hairnet. Now that's a pretty good magic trick that you'll be
able to take out the the כיפה kippah without removing the hairnet
on top because that would be our only concern a woman would
never fully expose her hair. But you know maybe you can like
you know if it's like basically like a type of a handkerchief
right so and it's you know first you put on a handkerchief
and then you put a hairnet on top of it you know
some type of a tighter fitting so you can make a little
you know lift up a little bit and pull out the handkerchief.
So that presumably is what we're talking about. It's something to cover
the hair. Is this a concern since it's under the hairnet that
you'll take it off? Technically she could without exposing her hair, is
that a concern or not? And here we see in a ברייתא
Beraita that this is debated. The תנא קמא says you can wear
it into the חצר Chatzer but not into the רשות הרבים Reshus
HaRabim and רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar says you
can even wear it in the רשות הרבים. Reshus HaRabim. I am
not afraid that a woman would take off this head covering under
her hairnet. So כלל אמר רבי שמעון בן אלעזר, Klal amar Rabbi
Shimon ben Elazar, כל שלמטה מן השבכה, kol she-le-mata min ha-shvacha, anything
under the hairnet, יוצאין בו, yotzin bo, you can go out into
רשות הרבים, Reshus HaRabim, we are not afraid she'll take it off.
I'm sorry, כל שלמעלה מן השבכה, kol she-le-mala min ha-shvacha, if it's
on top of the hairnet like a real hat or cap, אין
יוצאין בו, ein yotzin bo, you cannot take it off, oh, you
cannot go out because we're afraid you'll take it off. So what
have we seen? We've seen that everybody agrees if it's this thing
the slave wears it's a concern. If it's this thing, if it's
on top of a woman's hairnet, we would all agree that that's
a concern, she'll take it off. You know, a wool cap or
something, assuming it's something she might want to show her friends, something
nice. And the debate is the core case is that it's under
the hairnet where it's possible to take off without exposing her hair
but maybe a little difficult. And therefore the תנא קמא in our
משנה says no and רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar
says as long as it's under the hairnet that's fine. Okay now
the גמרא continues. מאי אסטמא? mai istama? What is this אסטמא istama
that we also said you can wear in your yard but not
in the רשות הרבים? Reshus HaRabim? אמר רבי אבהו בזיוני. Amar Rabbi
Avahu Bizyoni. Okay, that was helpful. מאי בזיוני? Mai Bizyoni? So what
is בזיוני? Bizyoni? אמר אביי אמר רב כליא פרוכי, Amar Abaye Amar
Rav kalya prukhei, which רש"י says basically it catches, it's something that
catches the sprouting hairs. A woman would wear a hairnet but some
of the hair would go outside the hairnet like maybe in the
front, maybe a little bit in the back. So you'd wear also
like a piece of cloth or some type of a felt around
the hair that would come out from the hairnet. Okay so that
also is a
problem because that strictly did not have to be covered and therefore
a woman might take it off. So that's what this is and
therefore it is a problem, a woman might come to take it
off. So תנו רבנן, Tano Rabbanan, our Rabbis taught, ג' דברים נאמרו
באסטמא, gimmel devarim neemru be-istama, three things were said by this אסטמא.
istama. אין בה משום כלאים, ein ba mishum kilayim, it's not a
כלאים kilayim issue, שעטנז sha'atnez issue, if it's wool and linen. Why
not? So רש"י says because it's basically it's like a felt and
it might be wool and linen pressed together but they're not actually
woven together. And now תוספות Tosafot has a question, I mean maybe
it's not biblical but like if they're, it should at least be
rabbinic. So תוספות Tosafot says two explanations. One is that yes but
not only is it pressed and not woven but also it is
very hard and it really does not like conform to the shape
of the body and does not warm the body. And one of
the definitions of it being defined as wearing and as clothing for
שעטנז sha'atnez is that
it like, you know, it's not like it's a flat thing on
top of the body but it actually like conforms a little and
provides warmth. So תוספות Tosafot says the combination of those two, that
it's hard and it's not really providing warmth and that it's only
pressed together means it's not שעטנז, sha'atnez, not שעטנז sha'atnez problem even
rabbinic. תוספות Tosafot has another interesting answer which is he says that
maybe what they, this thing was really a way of hanging jewelry
from it. That it wasn't, it was there just as a support
for jewelry and therefore it wasn't a clothing in its own right.
You didn't wear it because you wanted to wear the strap, you
wore it because you wanted to have the jewelry on you and
the strap was the way it's supporting the jewelry. And maybe that
makes it not a שעטנז sha'atnez issue because it's not there to
serve as clothing per se.
It could be both.
Right, yeah, so we just don't know exactly what the case was
but it could be, yes. You mean it could be both serving
both purposes. Absolutely. Right, but he's trying to explain why it's not
שעטנז sha'atnez
so he uses this description as a way of explaining that. Okay,
ואינה מטמאה בנגעים, ve-eina metamei bi-nega'im, it does not become טמא tamei
by leprosy, צרעת, tzara'at, נגעים. nega'im. Why not? Again because it's not
woven. And that is one of the criteria for becoming טמא tamei
for נגעים. nega'im. תוספות Tosafot has some discussions about that but we'll
leave it at that. ואין יוצאין בו לרשות הרבים, ve-ein yotzin bo
le-reshus ha-rabim, you cannot bring it out to רשות הרבים reshus ha-rabim
again because you might remove it because it's not strictly covering the
hair that needs to be covered. So what we're afraid a woman
would remove it. משום רבי שמעון אמרו, mishum Rabbi Shimon amru, in
the name of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon they said, אף אין בה
משום עטרות כלות, af ein ba mishum atarot kallot, that even you
do not have the problem of the, of like the, what do
you call it? The head ornaments that brides would wear. תניא במסכת
סוטה Tanya be-Masechet Sotah that they, after the wars of Vespasian after
they prohibited you know in order to remember the destruction of Jerusalem
and the oppression and so on, that brides should no longer be
wearing should wear like a certain degree of jewelry, these certain types
of crowns that they used to wear. So he said that that
doesn't fall, this type of thing would not fall into that category.
Which by the way supports תוספות's Tosafot's idea that they would hang
jewelry from it. It seems like it is something that is very
much a very much of jewelry. We have two more minutes, so
let's try to just finish this thought. ושמואל אמר Ve-Shmuel amar top
of נ"ח עמוד א', Nun Chet amud alef, שמואל Shmuel says כבלא
דעבדא תנן. kavla de-avda tnan. No, actually if it's the כבלא kavla
of the head, that's okay. We're only talking about this sort of
scarf, let's say underneath the hair net, that's not a problem. We're
only talking about, the משנה's only talking about the one that slaves
wore. That's the issue. So גמרא says ומי אמר שמואל הכי? U-mi
amar Shmuel hachi? Did שמואל Shmuel really say that? והאמר שמואל יוצא
עבד בחותם שבצוארו אבל לא בחותם שבכסותו. Ve-amar Shmuel yotzei eved be-chotam
she-be-tzavaro aval lo be-chotam she-bik-suto. So how could שמואל Shmuel say that
the thing of slaves is a problem? שמואל Shmuel says that a
slave is allowed to wear the seal around his neck. He's just
not allowed to wear the seal on his clothing. So because maybe
that's more easy to take off, the seal on your clothing and
you won't get in as much trouble, but the seal around your
neck you're allowed to wear. So how could he say that's what
our משנה's talking about? So גמרא says לא קשיא הא דעביד ליה
רביה הא דעביד איהו לנפשיה. Lo kashya, ha de-avid lei rabei ha
de-avid ihu le-nafshei. It depends who told him he had to wear
the seal. If his master told him he had to wear the
seal, then he's not going to take it off. Okay, and then
that's why he says the seal around the neck is okay. If
he himself made the seal and he's not required by his master
to wear it, why he made it I don't know, but anyway,
then it will be a concern he'll take it off and that's
the case in our משנה. Just read two more lines to finish
this point. The גמרא says במאי אוקימתא להא דשמואל? Be-mai ukimta le-ha
de-Shmuel? What did you say שמואל Shmuel is talking about? דעביד ליה
רביה, De-avid lei rabei, that when his master made it, that's when
he can go out with it because we're not afraid he'll take
it off? So if that's true, בחותם שבכסותו אמאי לא? be-chotam she-bik-suto
amai lo? Why is it a problem on his clothing? If his
master is making him wearing it, he's not going to take it
off whether it's on his body or his clothing. So why did
you say on the clothing was a problem? So the גמרא says
דילמא מיפסק ומרתע. Dilma mifsik ve-mirta. No, because what will happen is
the seal will break off and he'll be afraid because people will
think he took the seal off. By the way, this is very
evocative I got to tell you about the yellow star and the
taking it off and then you see that it was removed. So
anyway, so he's afraid that it'll fall off and he's going to
be afraid that his master will think he willfully took it off.
ומפליי ומחיה ליה אכתפיה U-miflei u-machei lei a-katfei and he'll fold up
his garment, he'll take off his garment off, his outer garment, and
he'll carry it on his shoulders. So nobody will see he's wearing
his garment without this.
כי דרב יצחק בר יוסף Ki de-Rav Yitzchak bar Yosef and it's
the concern of רב יצחק בר יוסף, Rav Yitzchak bar Yosef, דאמר
רב יצחק בר יוסף אמר רבי יוחנן היוצא בטלית כפולה ומונחת על
כתיפיו, de-amar Rav Yitzchak bar Yosef amar Rabbi Yochanan, ha-yotzei be-tallis kefula
u-menachas a-katfeio, if you have your garment folded up on your shoulder,
בשבת חייב חטאת be-Shabbos chayav chatas that's carrying, I don't care it's
a garment, you're not wearing it. So therefore yes, his master said
he has to wear it and he's going to get in big
trouble if he doesn't. But nevertheless if it's on his garment, he's
not going to willfully take it off but if it falls off,
that will lead to a case of carrying. Okay, whereas on his
body, that presumably is not a
concern because what's he going to do? It fell off. So the
גמרא says וכי הא דאמר ליה שמואל לרב חיננא בר שילא כולו
רבנן דבי ריש גלותא, Ve-chi ha de-amar lei Shmuel le-Rav Chinana bar
Shila kulu rabbanan de-bei resh galusa, so we remember the ריש גלותא?
Resh Galusa? So they also would wear signs on their garments. All
of the rabbis in the house of the ריש גלותא Resh Galusa
לא ליפקו בסריי ולא חתימי lo lipku be-sarye ve-lo chatime cannot go
out with their garments that have these signs on them on שבת
because they might fall off and then they'll have to, they'll take
their garment off and fold it, we're afraid they'll forget they'll carry
it because they'll be so concerned about being caught without the sign
on their garment. לבר מינך, Le-bar minach, but you're excluded. So why?
רב חיננא בר שילא. Rav Chinana bar Shila. דלא קפידי עלך דבי
ריש גלותא, De-lo kefidi alach de-bei resh galusa, because if you don't
have the sign on your garment, they'll give you a pass. But
they who will get in trouble, they can't wear it. So on
the one hand, if they'll get in trouble we'll say shouldn't be
a problem, you won't come to take it off. But on the
garment we're concerned even though you won't willfully take it off, it
might fall off and then you'll take the garment off so as
not to be found out and get in trouble, and that's the
concern of carrying. So that's the issue about the slave, and we
also have the issue about the hair net, and we will continue
with more issues of what you can wear and what you can
carry on שבת.